Inventory of the Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection D-394
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
1920 Due to the popularity of American football, rugby had almost disappeared from the United States except for California. The Olympic Games Committee granted Californians permission to form the United States Olympic Rugby Team for the upcoming Olympic Games in Antwerp, Belgium. Slater was one of the first players chosen for the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team. The team was mainly made up of students from California universities as well as recently graduated club players. Dan Carroll, an Australian gold medalist of the 1908 games and naturalized U.S. citizen, was both player and coach for the team. April-September. The Seventh Olympic Games were held in Antwerp, Belgium. The U.S. and France entered the rugby competition. As European champions, the French believed themselves to be far superior to the inexperienced U.S. team and only reluctantly consented to play the Americans. June 30. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team sailed from New York on an overcrowded Army transport ship, the Sherman, arriving in Antwerp, Belgium thirteen days later. July-September. In Antwerp, the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was housed in a converted school. Meals were served at their quarters, and buses transported the athletes to and from practice and competition. Sept. 5. The rugby match between France and the U.S. was played at Antwerp Stadium. Unexpectedly, the United States beat France 8-0. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team won the gold medal. Slater became the first University of California, Davis alumnus to win an Olympic gold medal. Sept. 19-Oct. 10. The loss to the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team stunned the French government. They asked the American team to tour France and play French all-star teams. The Americans won three out of the four matches they played.
1923 September. The U. S. Olympic Committee agreed to send a rugby team to the 1924 Olympic Games in Paris despite the fact that rugby had not been played competitively in the United States for almost a decade. The Committee did not provide travel funds, so players had to use their own money to get to Paris.
1924 Babe Slater was chosen as Captain of the United States Olympic Rugby Team. Brother, Norman Slater was chosen as a member of the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team. He was thirty, married, had two children, and worked in San Francisco. Linn Farish of Woodland, California had played on the Stanford Rugby Team and was also chosen as a member of the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team. March. The Woodland Democrat organized "The Babe Slater Friendship Fund" as a testimonial of friendship and token of the community's appreciation of the modest all-around sportsman. The Friendship Fund allowed a maximum donation of fifty cents. Slater was so popular that 510 people (including 130 grammar school boys) contributed to the fund, which was used to buy Slater a gold watch and chain, an elk's tooth charm, and a gold card and receipt case. Circa March. Woodland's Yolo Post No. 77, American Legion presented Slater with a suitcase engraved with his initials and a receipt, which acknowledged that his dues were paid in full for one year. Circa April 2. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team climbed aboard the Overland Limited.They were accompanied by Charles Austin as coach and Sam Goodman, President of the Pacific Athletic Association, as manager. The twenty-three member team included seven members who were veterans of the 1920 Olympic Games. April 7. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team sailed from New York on the America. Circa April 20. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team landed at Plymouth, England. The team played three exhibition games in London against British rugby clubs in order to "get in shape" before the Paris Olympic Games. April. In England, the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was joined by Allen C. Valentine. Valentine, a Rhodes Scholar and All-American, was the only member of the team who was not from California. Circa April 27. The British Olympic Association gave a dinner for the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team at the Piccadilly Hotel in London. Circa April 28. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team arrived in Paris. The team was made up of superb athletes including California football and basketball All-Americans. Many had never played rugby, but Coach Austin relied on his team's size, speed, stamina, and raw athletic ability to compensate for its technical deficiencies. Circa April-May. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was the target of French hostility. After immigration officials mistakenly refused the team entry into France and the American players forced their way off ship and onto dry land, the French press labeled the team, "street fighters and saloon brawlers." When American rugby team members ventured outside their Paris hotel, they were insulted and even spat upon by the French. Circa May. Cash and other possessions were stolen from the U.S. Olympic Team's dressing room while they were at practice. May. Three teams entered the Olympic rugby competition in Paris: France, the United States, and Romania. May 4. France won their rugby match against Romania, 61-3. May 11. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team defeated Romania 37-0. The French crowd booed every American score, but both the American and French press noted the lack of violence and skilled nature of American play, along with the Americans' size and fitness. May 18. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team won the gold medal by defeating France 17-3 at Colombes Stadium, which was filled with 50,000 spectators. The French rugby team was expected to easily beat the inexperienced American team. During the game, the French were devastated by American football-style tackling. The hits were within the rules of the game. The humiliating defeat of the French team angered their fans, who rioted in the stands and assaulted American supporters. The French fans threw bottles and rocks at the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team and tried to break through the tall wire fence that surrounded the playing field. Tens of thousand of hostile onlookers jeered the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team during the medal ceremony, the raising of the American flag, and the playing of the "Star Spangled Banner". After the ceremony, the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team was rescued from the rioting crowd by dozens of gendarmes. Due in part to the bad behavior of the French crowd and the lack of international participation in Olympic rugby matches, rugby was not included in future Olympic games. The French government later apologized for the behavior of the French fans, and soon after, the French press began to portray the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team as heroes. May 18. A banquet was given by the French Rugby Federation at Palais D'Orsay in honor of the Olympic Rugby Games. The U.S. Olympic Rugby Team attended this official banquet. The Prince of Wales was also a guest. May 19. American Friends of the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team, including Senator James D. Phelan, gave a banquet in honor of the team's Olympic victory. The banquet was held at the Inter-Allied Club of Paris. Many prominent Californians attended. Senator Phelan presented the team with medals and a statue that symbolized victory. May 21. Coach Austin and eight players left Paris for Cherbourg on the first leg of their journey home. They sailed for New York on the steamship, George Washington.The rest of the U.S. Olympic Rugby Team went their separate ways. Circa June 4. After traveling to Belgium and Switzerland, the Slater brothers, departed from Cherbourg and sailed for New York on the S.S. Leviathan. Circa June 15. The Slater brothers returned to the San Francisco Bay Area. Circa June. Mr. and Mrs. Robert (Bob) Lockhart held an open house in honor of Babe Slater upon his return to Woodland, California from the Paris Olympic Games. Circa June. Slater resumed farming in Woodland.
1924-1925 Dec. 25-Jan. 1. Rugby matches were held at Brockton Point, Vancouver, British Columbia. The California All-Stars (mainly made up of U.S. Olympic Rugby Team members, and including Babe Slater) beat the University of British Columbia 9-0, the "Reps" beat California 3-0, and California beat the Mainland All-Stars 15-0 in the final and deciding contest of the three game series.
1927 Dec. 4. Woodland's American Legion football team won the California State Championship. Woodland beat Merced 6-0 to win the Championship game, which was held at Kezar Stadium in San Francisco. Slater both played for and coached the Woodland team.
Circa 1927 Slater moved to Clarksburg, California. At Gus Olson's urging, he bought 100 acres of rich farming land located in the Holland Land Company subdivision at Clarksburg.
Circa 1927-1955 On his Clarksburg farm, Slater raised crops including: alfalfa, asparagus, barley, beet and carrot seed, dry beans, peas, safflower, sugar beets, tomatoes, and wheat.
1928 October. Norman Slater moved to Clarksburg in order to farm with his brother. Norman had been a mechanic for the Associated Oil Company in San Francisco.
Circa 1930s-1960s Slater was active in University of California, Davis groups including the Cal Aggie Alumni Association, Friends of the Davis Campus, the UC Davis Alumni Agricultural Advisory Committee, the UC Davis Alumni Scholarship Foundation, and Sword in Sandals.
1930-1931 May 5. The Clarksburg Community Church Council approved the building of scout cabins in Clarksburg. A committee was formed with Slater as Chairman of Construction, and the community worked together to build the cabins.
1932 Slater married Virginia Cave at the Clarksburg Community Church.
1932-1933 Slater was one of a group of Clarksburg farmers who leased a cannery in order to can and sell their asparagus crops.
1933 Daughter, Marilyn was born. She was the Slaters' only child.
Circa 1946 A committee of Clarksburg residents (including Babe and Norman Slater) with the help of the Yolo County Extension Service initiated the establishment of a fire district for Clarksburg.
1947 April 19. Babe Slater, Robert G. Sproul, Claude P. Hutchison, Judge Peter J. Shields, Robert (Bob) Lockhart, J. E. Coke, G. H. Hecke, and Stanley Freeborn were among the honored guests at Picnic Day on the UC Davis campus. Norman Slater was elected fire chief and served until retirement in 1962. Babe Slater served as a commissioner of the Clarksburg Fire Department.
Circa 1948 Mother, Louise, died.
1951 April 14. Slater and California Governor Earl Warren were among the honored guests at Picnic Day on the University of California, Davis campus. Circa January. Slater was elected President of the Yolo County Farm Bureau. Over the years, he and Mrs. Slater went on many Farm Bureau trips including travel to Australia, Belgium, Germany, Japan, and Mexico.
1952 January. Slater was reelected as Yolo County Farm Bureau President, and the Bureau held its 37th annual meeting in Woodland. More than 600 persons attended the business meeting and accompanying bean feed, awards presentations, and entertainment. December. Thirty-five Yolo County Farm Bureau members including Mr. and Mrs. Babe Slater boarded a special train at Davis, California, joining 175 northern Californians and 255 southern Californians on their way to a ten-day American Farm Bureau Federation convention in Seattle, Washington. The group also toured Victoria, British Columbia.
1955 Circa May. Daughter, Marilyn graduated from the University of California, Davis. She had been a yell leader (1955), a member of the Alpha Omega sorority (1955), a member of the Cal Club (1954, 1955), Director of Reception for Picnic Day (1954), Junior Class Secretary (1954), a member of the Rally Committee (1953, 1955), Picnic Day Secretary (1953), and a homecoming princess (1952, 1953, 1955). August. Daughter, Marilyn married Richard McCapes in Sacramento. Slater retired from farming.
Circa 1955 After retirement, Mr. and Mrs. Babe Slater bought a vacation home at Dillon Beach near Bodega Bay, California.
1956 April 21. Slater judged the Picnic Day Parade at the University of California, Davis.
1956, 1957 Active in the Cal Aggie Alumni Association, Slater arranged reunions for the classes of 1916 and 1917 to be held on the University of California, Davis campus during Picnic Day. The classes of 1914 and 1915 were also invited.
1957, 1958 April. Mr. and Mrs. Slater were among the honored guests at Picnic day on the University of California, Davis campus.
1961 April. Slater, Robert (Bob) Lockhart, and other "old-timers" rode in the University of California, Davis Picnic Day Parade. They would attend a reunion of the Class of 1916.
1965 Jan. 30. Colby E. Babe Slater died. The Calpha agricultural fraternity established the Colby E. "Babe" Slater Memorial Athletic Award at the University of California, Davis. This annual award went each spring to the Davis student selected as Athlete of the Year. Associated with the award was the "Babe" Slater Perpetual Athletic Trophy.
Circa 1970 Brother, Norman Slater, a longtime Clarksburg resident, moved to Sacramento.
1973 June 14. Babe Slater was posthumously inducted into the Woodland Athletic Hall of Fame. His wife, Virginia, accepted the award at the first annual awards dinner in Woodland.
1980 Oct. 10. Babe Slater was posthumously inducted into the newly formed Cal Aggies Athletic Hall of Fame at the University of California, Davis. His wife, Virginia, accepted the award at the first annual induction banquet. Chancellor James H. Meyer presented each hall-of-famer with a plaque commemorating his induction.
1991 Nov. 15. Mrs. Slater (Virginia Cave Slater) died.
2003 December. Marilyn Slater McCapes and Richard H. McCapes donated the Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection to Special Collections at the General Library of the University of California, Davis.
2004 February. Marilyn Slater McCapes and Richard H. McCapes presented Intercollegiate Athletics at the University of California, Davis with Babe Slater's two Olympic gold medals.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Colby E. "Babe" Slater Collection spans the years 1906 to 2001, but the bulk of the collection is made up of materials dating from 1917 to 1957. The collection is arranged in seven series: 1. Diaries, 2. Correspondence, 3. Publications, 4. Ephemera, 5. Photographic Material, 6. Scrapbook, and 7. Realia. Most of the Slater Collection focuses on Slater and the United States Olympic Rugby Team winning gold medals at the 1920 Olympic Games in Antwerp, Belgium and the 1924 Olympic Games in Paris. The collection also contains material pertaining to subjects such as the University of California, Davis (formerly the University Farm); World War I; farming; travel; Yolo County, California; the Berkeley (Calif.) High School Rugby Team; and Woodland, California's American Legion football team. Highlights of the Slater Collection include photographs of Picnic Day 1916 at the University Farm; Slater's diary kept while he served in the United States Army during the First World War; correspondence related to a forty-year reunion of the University of California, Davis' Class of 1917; a list of those who contributed to the "Babe" Slater Friendship Fund; scrapbook items such as clippings, photographs, and other memorabilia from the Olympic games; Slater's two Olympic diplomas; and some of his medals. Slater's two Olympic gold medals are housed at Intercollegiate Athletics at the University of California, Davis.
Yolo County (Calif.) -- History; Rugby football; Ranching -- California -- Yolo County; World War, 1914-1918; Sports -- History -- 20th century; Agriculture -- California -- Yolo County; Football; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; University of California, Davis -- Students; California Aggie Alumni Association; Olympic Games (7th: 1920: Antwerp, Belgium); Olympic Games (8th: 1924: Paris, France)
- Diaries, 1919-1922; Series 1; 2 Volumes
  Scope and Contents note
  In the first diary, Slater recorded events of his service in the United States Army on the Western Front during the First World War. In the 1922 diary, Slater kept brief records of his work managing a farm on the Conaway Ranch in Woodland, California.
  - World War I Diary, June 1918-May 1919; D394.1.1; Slater, Colby E.; 1 volume (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contents
    In this diary, Slater recorded events of his service in the United States Army on the Western Front during the First World War.
    World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, American; Diaries
  - World War I Diary Transcript, June 1918-May 1919; D394.1.3; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Conaway Ranch, Woodland (Calif.) Diary, 1922; D394.1.2; Slater, Colby E.; 1 volume (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content
    In this 1922 diary, Slater kept brief records of his work managing a farm on the Conaway Ranch in Woodland, California.
    Farmers -- California -- Yolo County.
- Correspondence, 1920-1973; Series 2; 19 folders
  Arranged chronologically. The 1924 letters relate to the Paris Olympic Games. The 1948 letter has to do with Slater's choice of farming as his life's work. The 1956 and 1957 letters and class rosters pertain to Slater's efforts to organize Picnic Day class reunions for the University of California, Davis' classes of 1914, 1915, 1916, and 1917. The 1973 letter has to do with Slater's posthumous induction into the Woodland (Calif.) Athletic Hall of Fame.
  - Slater, Colby E. to Lockhart, Robert, September 20, 1920; 1 envelope and 4 sheets (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    Rugby football; Rugby football teams -- United States; Slater, Colby E.
  - Bower, E. to Dagg, E., April 2, 1924; D394.2.1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ? to Slater, Colby E. Babe, May 19, [1924]; D394.2.2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poston, A. J. to Scott, J. B., June 11, 1924; D394.2.20 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
    Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; Slater, Norman B. (Norman Bernard), 1894-1979 -- Archives
  - Slater, Colby E. Babe to Lockhart, Marilyn, May 4, 1948; D394.2.3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopy.
  - Olympic Club to Slater, Colby E. Babe, December 1, 1949; D394.2.23 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    Includes member roster
    Olympic athletes -- United States; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; Olympic Games (8th: 1924: Paris, France)
  - Coke, Sterling D. to [Voorhies, Edwin C.], April 2, 1956; D394.2.4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Duffy, W. J., Jr., to Slater, Colby E. Babe, April 11, 1956; D394.2.5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Spafford, F. E. to Slater, Colby E. Babe and Blossom, Bob, Jan. 17, 1957; D394.2.6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ed? to Slater, Colby E. Babe, March 2, 1957; D394.2.7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Slater, Colby E. Babe and Blossom, Bob to Cal-Aggie Alumni, Class of 1917, March 13, 1957; D394.2.8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    General note
    form letter.
  - Wood, Leonard C. to Slater, Colby E. Babe, March 19, 1957; D394.2.9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Duffy, W. J., Jr., to Slater, Colby E. Babe, March 23, 1957; D394.2.10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter and enclosed report.
  - Ho, Dean to Slater, Colby E. Babe, March 29, 1957; D394.2.11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Seares, Fritz to Slater, Colby E. Babe, April 3, 1957; D394.2.12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bath, George H. to Slater, Colby E. Babe, April 8, 1957; D394.2.13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ? to Slater, Colby E. Babe, April 9, 1957; D394.2.14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ed? to Slater, Colby E. Babe, April 21, 1957; D394.2.15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1914, 1915, 1916, 1917, roster, compiled, circa 1957; D394.2.16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Class of 1917, roster, compiled, circa 1957; D394.2.17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Aggie Alumni, Sacramento, Yolo, and Solano Counties, roster, compiled, circa 1957; D394.2.18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Coke, Sterling D. to Slater, Colby E. "Babe", circa April 1964; D394.2.25 (Box 1, Folder 20A)
    Four sheets: note and carbon copies of three letters
    Slater, Colby E.
  - Hickey, Vern B. to Slater, Virginia, October 18, 1965; D394.2.24 (Box 1, Folder 20B)
    Envelope and one sheet
    Slater, Colby E.; Slater, Virgina C., 1909-1991
  - Tavernetti, J.R. to Slater, Virginia, September 28, 1965; D394.2.23 (Box 1, Folder 20C)
    Envelope and three sheets
  - Klenhard, Dick to Slater, Virginia, June 6, 1973; D394.2.19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sproul, Robert to Slater, Colby. E., undated; D394.2.22 (Box 1, Folder 21A)
    Slater, Colby E.; Sproul, Robert Gordon, 1891-1975 -- Correspondence; University of California, Berkeley
- Publications, 1912-2004; Series 3; 23 folders.
  Arranged by subject in the following subseries: University of California, Davis; World War I; Seventh Olympic Games; Eighth Olympic Games; Travel; Yolo County (Calif.); and Other. Contains serials, clippings, maps, and travel guides.
  - University of California, Davis, 1917-2009; Subseries 3.1; 5 folders; 2 linear feet
    Arranged chronologically. Contains clippings and serials.
    - Clippings, Picnic Day activities will soon commence, February 9, 1917; D394.3.1.1 (Box 6, Folder 1.1)
      original and copy
      2 sheets
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Arichives; University of California, Davis -- History; University Farm Agricola; Picnic Day
    - Clippings, Entire student body of University Farm will prepare campus for great influx of Picnic Day visitors, February 9, 1917; D394.3.1.2 (Box 6, Folder 1.2)
      2 pages
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Student activities -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; University Farm Agricola
    - Clippings, Date of Picnic Day is officially decided, February 16, 1917; D394.3.1.3 (Box 6, Folder 1.3)
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; University Farm Agricola; Picnic Day
    - Clippings, Committee Plans Picnic Day Activities, March 2, 1917; D394.3.1.4 (Box 6, Folder 1.4)
      Original and copy.
    - Clipping, Students may choose committee to serve, February 16, 1917; D394.3.1.5 (Box 6, Folder 1.5)
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Student activities -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; University Farm Agricola; Picnic Day
    - Clipping, Plans under way for picnic day at University Farm, undated; D394.3.1.6 (Box 6, Folder 1.6)
    - Clippings, Picnic Day chairmen planning for great day, February 23, 1917; D394.3.1.7 (Box 6, Folder 1.7)
      Original and photocopy.
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University Farm Agricola; University of California, Davis -- History; Picnic Day
    - Clippings, "Babe Slater" appointed Picnic Day chairman, February 2, 1917; D394.3.1.8 (Box 6, Folder 1.8)
    - Clipping, Colby Slater, star athlete at the University Farm at Davis, will be general chairman of the annual Picnic Day at Davis this spring, February 9, 1917; D394.3.1.9 (Box 6, Folder 1.9)
      Reprint of 1917 article.
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History
    - Clipping, C.E. (Babe) Slater was general chairman for the highly successful Picnic Day held at the University Farm at Davis, May 8, 1917; D394.3.1.10 (Box 6, Folder 1.10)
      Festivals -- California -- Davis; Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; Picnic Day
    - Clippings, Undefeated football team of the University Farm, undated; D394.3.1.11 (Box 6, Folder 1.11)
      original and copy.
      Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History
    - University Farm Agricola: Ninth Annual Farmer's Day, April 28, 1917, April 13, 1917; D394.3.1.12 (Box 6, Folder 1.12)
      Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University of California, Davis -- History; University Farm Agricola
    - University Farm Agricola, May 4, 1917; D394.3.1.13 (Box 6, Folder 1.13)
      Slater, Colby E. -- Archives; University Farm Agricola; University of California, Davis -- History